Finding Aid for North Central Association of Colleges and Schools, Michigan State Office, Records. 1895-1994
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
North Central Association of Colleges and Schools, Michigan State Office, Records 1895-1994, 1919-1994
North Central Association of Colleges and Schools. Michigan State Office.
34 linear feet
Regional organization for accrediting colleges universities and secondary schools, includes administrative records and accreditation reports for high schools in Kent, Houghton, Washtenaw, and Wayne counties in Michigan.
98112 Bh/2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The records were donated by the North Central Association of Colleges and Schools, Michigan State Office (Donor No. 8677 ) in 1998.
The record group is open for research.
The North Central Association of Colleges and Schools (NCA) was founded in 1895 with the purpose of establishing closer relations between the colleges and secondary schools of the North Central States. There were originally ten states that were members in the Association: Illinois, Indiana, Iowa, Kansas, Michigan, Minnesota, Missouri, Nebraska, Ohio, and Wisconsin. Other states joined the NCA gradually, and by 1956 Arizona, Arkansas, Colorado, Montana, New Mexico, North Dakota, Oklahoma, South Dakota, West Virginia, and Wyoming had become members.
The first official meeting of the Association occurred on April 1, 1896, and meetings have been held annually since that point in time. The meetings for the first several years focused around the exchange and discussion of different viewpoints on the educational concerns of the day. Legislation addressing the matters discussed was not a consideration at this point in time.
By 1900, however, the Association had set up a commission on Secondary Schools. This commission was comprised of three separate committees which had the task to come up with a set of standards that would apply for all institutions. In 1910 this goal was accomplished when the committee listed established courses of study comprised of units (which were uniform) for the high school curriculum. Using this list of standards, the Association officially accredited 156 secondary schools in 1911. During this time, the committee was also examining accrediting and standardizing colleges. The Association officially accredited colleges for the first time in 1912. By 1956 there were 3,398 secondary schools and 382 colleges, universities, and junior colleges that were members of the North Central Association.
Individual secondary schools that were interested in joining the Association were inspected by an individual from the NCA. A report containing information for that school year was also completed. In the early years this appears to have been done by the inspector. Then in the late 1910's or early 1920's, the responsibility for filling out this report and sending it to the NCA appears to have been transferred to the schools themselves. If the school was accepted into the Association, then an annual report would have to be completed each subsequent year to make sure that the school was still complying with NCA standards. Periodic inspections by an individual from the NCA were also done for this purpose.
The NCA is still active today, and the process of evaluation of schools by reports and inspection is still in place.
The records of the North Central Association of Colleges and Schools, Michigan State Office are divided into two series: High School Records and Administrative/Organizational Records.
The largest part of the record group consists of accreditation reports containing information on schools in the Kent, Houghton, Washtenaw, and Wayne counties in Michigan. Also included in the record group are a number of bound volumes containing information from the proceedings of the North Central Association's annual meeting, as well as a variety of papers and articles relating to the educational issues of the day.
Subjects:
Education, Secondary.; High Schools--Accreditation.; Houghton County (Mich.); Kent County (Mich.); North Central Association of Colleges and Schools. Michigan State Office.; Schools--Michigan.; Schools--Michigan--Houghton County.; Schools--Michigan--Kent County.; Schools--Michigan--Washtenaw County.; Schools--Michigan--Wayne County.; Washtenaw County (Mich.); Wayne County (Mich.)
- High School Records
  The High School Records series contains the school accreditation reports for high schools in the Kent, Houghton, Washtenaw, and Wayne counties in Michigan. The reports include lists of classes offered by the school, lists of new teachers for each school year, a letter of accreditation, lists of any violations of the North Central Association's regulations committed by the school, and correspondence between the school and the Association. Some of the older records also contain information about teacher salaries (including comparisons between the salaries of the male and female teachers), information about the school buildings, and student information (such as number enrolled in a particular class) broken down by gender.
  - Allen Park
    - Allen Park High School 1953-1993/94, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor
    - Community High School 1991/92-1993/94 (Box 1)
    - Huron High School 1981/82-1993/94, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Pioneer High School 1981/82-1993/94, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - University High School 1926-1967/68 (Box 1)
  - Belleville
    - Belleville High School
      - 1941-1971/72, 4 folders (Box 1)
      - 1972/73-1993/94, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Byron Center
    - Byron Center High School 1987/88-1993/94 (Box 2)
  - Caledonia
    - Caledonia High School 1954-1993/94, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Calumet
    - Calumet High School 1919-1993/94, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Cedar Springs
    - Cedar Springs High School 1930-1993/94, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Chelsea
    - Chelsea High School 1927-1983/84, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Chelsea High School 1987/88-1993/94 (Box 3)
  - Comstock Park
    - Comstock Park High School 1991/92-1993/94 (Box 3)
  - Dearborn
    - Dearborn High School 1915-1993/94, 5 folders (Box 3)
    - Divine Child High School 1993/94 (Box 3)
    - The Edison Institute 1948/49-1951/52 (Box 3)
    - Edsel Ford High School 1955-1993/94, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Fordson High School 1925-1993/94, 5 folders (Box 3)
    - Harvey H. Lowrey 1952/53-1968/69, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Dearborn Heights
    - Annapolis High School 1970/71-1993/94, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Crestwood High School 1962/63-1993/94, 5 folders (Box 4)
    - Riverside High School 1961/62-1983/84, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Hamilton J. Robichaud High School 1963/64-1989/90, 3 folders (Box 4)
      - 1963/64-1989/90, 3 folders (Box 4)
      - 1990/91-1993/94 (Box 5)
  - Detroit
    - General 1937-1948 (Box 5)
    - Cass Technical High School 1921/22-1993/94, 8 folders (Box 5)
    - Central High School
      - 1902-1982/83, 5 folders (Box 5)
      - 1983/84-1993/94 (Box 6)
    - Chadsey High School 1934/35-1993/94, 6 folders (Box 6)
    - Cody High School 1954/55-1993/94, 6 folders (Box 6)
    - Thomas M. Cooley High School
      - 1928/29-1949/50 (Box 6)
      - 1950/51-1993/94, 6 folders (Box 7)
    - Crockett Vocational Technical Center 1991/92-1993/94 (Box 7)
    - Edwin Denby High School 1930/31-1993/94, 7 folders (Box 7)
    - Detroit Country Day School 1927, 1929 (Box 7)
    - Detroit High School for the Fine and Performing Arts 1992/93 (Box 8)
    - Dominican High School 1943/44-1993/94, 5 folders (Box 8)
    - Eastern High School 1919/20-1967/68, 3 folders (Box 8)
    - Jared W. Finney High School 1964/65-1993/94, 4 folders (Box 8)
    - Henry Ford High School
      - 1962/63-1976/77, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - 1977/78-1993/94, 3 folders (Box 9)
    - Girls Catholic Central High School 1957/58 (Box 9)
    - High School of Commerce 1927/28-1963/64, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Charles F. Kettering High School 1968/69-1993/94, 4 folders (Box 9)
    - David Mackenzie High School
      - 1931/32-1977/78, 7 folders (Box 9)
      - l 1978/79-1993/94, 3 folders (Box 10)
    - Martin Luther King High School 1968/69-1993/94, 4 folders (Box 10)
    - Mumford High School 1953/54-1993/94, 6 folders (Box 10)
    - Murray-Wright High School
      - 1970/71-1977/78 (Box 10)
      - 1978/79-1993/94, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Northeastern High School 1919/20-1981/82, 5 folders (Box 11)
    - Northern High School 1919/20-1993/94, 7 folders (Box 11)
    - Northwestern High School
      - 1919/20-1942/43 (Box 11)
      - 1945/46-1993/94, 6 folders (Box 12)
    - Osborn High School 1958/59-1993/94, 4 folders (Box 12)
    - John J. Pershing High School
      - 1930/31-1969/70, 3 folders (Box 12)
      - 1970/71-1993/94, 3 folders (Box 13)
    - Redford High School 1925/26-1993/94, 7 folders (Box 13)
    - Renaissance High School 1983/84-1993/94 (Box 13)
    - Southeastern High School
      - 1919/20-1966/67, 3 folders (Box 13)
      - 1967/68-1993/94, 4 folders (Box 14)
    - Southwestern High School 1906/07-1993/94, 7 folders (Box 14)
    - University of Detroit Jesuit High School and Academy, 3 folders
      - 1919/20-1976/77, 3 folders (Box 14)
      - 1988/89-1993/94 (Box 15)
    - Western High School 1919/20-1993/94, 5 folders (Box 15)
  - Dexter
    - Dexter High School 1921/22-1993/94, 2 folders (Box 15)
  - East Grand Rapids
    - East Grand Rapids High School 1924/25-1993/94, 4 folders (Box 15)
  - Ecorse
    - Ecorse High School, 2 folders
      - 1930/31-1967/68, 2 folders (Box 15)
      - 1968/69-1993/94, 3 folders (Box 16)
  - Flat Rock
    - Flat Rock High School 1928/29-1993/94, 6 folders (Box 16)
    - Woodhaven High School 1974/75-1993/94, 2 folders (Box 16)
  - Garden City
    - Garden City High School (East)
      - 1954/55-1991/92, 4 folders (Box 16)
      - 1992/93-1993/94 (Box 17)
    - Garden City West High School 1965/66-1981/82, 2 folders (Box 17)
  - Grand Rapids
    - Catholic Central High School 1906-1948, 2 folders (Box 34)
    - Catholic Central High School 1949/50-1993/94, 3 folders (Box 17)
    - Creston High School 1926-1946 (Box 34)
    - Grand Rapids Central High School 1929-1948 (Box 34)
    - Grand Rapids Central High School 1919/20-1993/94, 4 folders (Box 17)
    - Creston High School 1949/50-1993/94, 4 folders (Box 17)
    - Forest Hills Central High School 1965/66-1976/77 (Box 17)
    - Forest Hills Central High School 1977/78-1993/94, 2 folders (Box 18)
    - Forest Hills Northern High School 1978/79-1993/94, 2 folders (Box 18)
    - Girls Catholic Central 1927-1930 (Box 34)
    - Grand Rapids Christian High School 1925-1948 (Box 34)
    - Grand Rapids Christian High School 1949/50-1993/94, 3 folders (Box 18)
    - Marywood Academy 1925-1948 (Box 34)
    - Marywood Academy 1957/58-1959/60 (Box 18)
    - Mt. Mercy Academy 1924-1948 (Box 34)
    - Ottawa Hills High School 1926-1948 (Box 34)
    - Ottawa Hills High School 1949/50-1993/94, 5 folders (Box 18)
    - South High School 1919-1948 (Box 34)
    - Union High School 1949/50-1988/89, 3 folders (Box 18)
    - Union High School 1919-1948 (Box 34)
    - Union High School 1989/90-1993/94 (Box 19)
    - West Catholic High School 1991/92-1993/94 (Box 19)
  - Grandville
    - Grandville High School 1930/31-1993/94, 5 folders (Box 19)
  - Grosse Ile Township
    - Grosse Ile High School 1926/27-1993/94, 3 folders (Box 19)
  - Grosse Pointe
    - Grosse Pointe North High School 1969/70-1993/94, 3 folders (Box 19)
  - Hancock
    - Hancock Central High School (Box 19)
      - 1919/20-1980/81, 3 folders (Box 19)
    - 1987/88-1993/94 (Box 20)
  - Harper Woods
    - Harper Woods High School 1959/60-1993/94, 3 folders (Box 20)
    - Regina High School 1965/66 (Box 20)
  - Highland Park
    - Highland Park Community High School 1919/20-1993/94, 7 folders (Box 20)
  - Houghton
    - Houghton High School
      - 1919/20-1990/91, 3 folders (Box 20)
      - 1991/92-1993/94 (Box 21)
  - Inkster
    - Inkster High School 1956/57-1993/94, 3 folders (Box 21)
  - Kelloggsville
    - Kelloggsville High School 1958/59-1993/94, 3 folders (Box 21)
  - Kenowa Hills
    - Kenowa Hills High School 1964/65-1993/94, 2 folders (Box 21)
  - Kentwood
    - East Kentwood High School 1967/68-1993/94, 5 folders (Box 21)
  - Lake Linden
    - Lake Linden-Hubbell High School
      - 1922/23-1954/55 (Box 21)
      - 1955/56-1993/94, 3 folders (Box 22)
  - Lincoln Park
    - Lincoln Park High School 1936/37-1993/94, 6 folders (Box 22)
  - Livonia
    - Winston Churchill High School 1970/71-1993/94, 3 folders (Box 22)
    - Franklin High School, 4 folders
      - 1963/64-1970/71, 4 folders (Box 22)
      - 1971/72-1993/94, 2 folders (Box 23)
    - Adlai E. Stevenson High School 1967/68-1993/94, 6 folders (Box 23)
  - Lowell
    - Lowell High School 1919/20-1993/94, 4 folders (Box 23)
  - Manchester
    - Manchester High School 1987/88-1993/94 (Box 23)
  - Melvindale
    - Melvindale High School 1954/55-1993/94, 3 folders (Box 23)
  - Milan (Box 24)
    - Milan High School 1928/29-1993/94, 4 folders (Box 24)
  - Northview
    - Northview High School 1981/82-1983/84 (Box 24)
  - Northville
    - Northville High School 1905-1993/94, 4 folders (Box 24)
  - Osceola Township
    - Dollar Bay High School 1919/20-1993/94, 3 folders (Box 24)
  - Redford
    - Catholic Central High School 1992/93-1993/94 (Box 24)
    - Redford Union High School 1976/77-1993/94, 3 folders (Box 24)
  - Riverview
    - Riverview Community High School 1981/82-1993/94, 2 folders (Box 25)
  - Rockford
    - Rockford High School 1912-1993/94, 4 folders (Box 25)
  - Romulus
    - Romulus High School 1954/55-1993/94, 6 folders (Box 25)
  - Saline
    - Saline High School 1908-1993/94, 3 folders (Box 25)
  - Southgate
    - Southgate Anderson High School
      - 1962/63-1975/76 (Box 25)
      - 1976/77-1993/94, 2 folders (Box 26)
  - South Redford
    - Lee M. Thurston High School 1976/77-1993/94, 2 folders (Box 26)
  - Sparta
    - Sparta High School 1968/69-1993/94, 3 folders (Box 26)
  - Taylor
    - John F. Kennedy High School 1965/66-1993/94, 3 folders (Box 26)
    - Taylor Center High School (Box 26)
      - 1956/57-1991/92, 6 folders (Box 26)
      - 1992/93-1993/94 (Box 27)
    - Harry S. Truman High School 1973/74-1993/94, 3 folders (Box 27)
  - Trenton
    - Trenton High School 1914-1993/94, 6 folders (Box 27)
  - Wayne-Westland
    - William D. Ford Vocational/Technical Center 1991/92-1993/94 (Box 27)
    - John Glenn High School 1965/66-1993/94, 3 folders (Box 27)
    - Wayne Memorial High School
      - 1908-1960/61, 2 folders (Box 27)
      - 1961/62-1993/94, 4 folders (Box 28)
  - Westland
    - Westland Lutheran High School 1987/88-1993/94 (Box 28)
  - Whitmore Lake
    - Whitmore Lake High School 1991/92-1993/94 (Box 28)
  - Willow Run
    - Willow Run High School 1957/58-1993/94, 3 folders (Box 28)
  - Wyandotte
    - Theodore Roosevelt High School 1919/20-1993/94, 5 folders (Box 28)
  - Wyoming
    - Horizons High School 1991/92-1993/94 (Box 28)
    - Rogers High School 1958/59-1993/94, 3 folders (Box 29)
    - Wyoming Park High School 1960/61-1993/94, 3 folders (Box 29)
  - Ypsilanti
    - Lincoln High School 1924/25-1993/94, 3 folders (Box 29)
    - Roosevelt High School 1914-1968/69, 2 folders (Box 29)
    - Ypsilanti High School 1908-1975/76, 3 folders
      - 1908-1975/76, 3 folders (Box 29)
      - 1976/77-1993/94, 3 folders (Box 30)
- Administrative/Organizational Records
  The Administrative/Organizational Records series contains bound volumes of the North Central Association's meeting proceedings, from the preliminary meeting in 1895 to 1925. The proceedings include papers and addresses given by members of the Association, lists of the accredited schools (both colleges and high schools), a copy of the constitution of the Association (as well as any amendments made to it), and lists of the standards of admission into the Association. This series also contains bound volumes of the North Central Association Quarterly from 1926 to 1957. These reports still contain information on the annual meetings of the Association, but also contain a variety of papers and articles relating to the educational issues of the day (from the training of teachers, to the social and educational guidance of returning veterans from World War II). The reports also contain book reviews, lists of publications of the Association, and lists of accredited schools.
  - Proceedings
    - 1895-1914 (Box 30)
    - 1917-1919 (Box 30)
    - 1920-1923 (Box 30)
    - 1924-1925 (Box 30)
  - North Central Association Quarterly
    - 1926/27-1934/35 (Box 31)
      Volumes 1-9
    - 1935/36-1942/43 (Box 32)
      Volumes 10-17
    - 1943/44-1956/57 (Box 33)
      Volumes 18-32